Guide to the Merrill G. Burlingame Papers 1880-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Merrill G. Burlingame papers
1880-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Burlingame, Merrill G. (Merrill Gildea), 1901-1994
2245
Collection 2245, MtBC, us
30 linear feet
The Merrill G. Burlingame Papers are primarily research files that reflect Burlingame's lifelong interest in the history of Montana and the American West. Subjects represented are: the history of Bozeman and Gallatin County, Montana and associated individuals; the history of Montana State University and associated individuals; the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ); Captain Gustavus C. Doane, Second U.S. Cavalry; Montana Native Americans. There is also a small group of personal papers containing familial correspondence and genealogical information on the Burlingame family. Original documents created or collected by the William W. Alderson family, Gustavus C. Doane, and Harriette Cushman are also part of the Burlingame papers.
Subject file pertaining to Ray Burlingame in Series 10 has been closed for research until 2070.
Research files, personal papers, photographs, microfilm, and audiotapes created or collected by Merrill G. Burlingame were donated to Special Collections in 1991 and 1994 by Dr. Burlingame. Letters originally assigned collection number 495 were added on October 18, 2011. A response by Elmer Starch to "The Taylor Years," found in the stacks, was added in 2023.
Series 1 Biographical files
Series 2 Gallatin County research
Series 3 Montana and the pioneer west
Series 4 General correspondence
Series 5 Montana place names
Series 6 Indians
Series 7 MSC/MSU
Series 8 Organizations
Series 9 Clippings
Series 10 Personal papers
Series 11 Photographs
Series 12 Maps
Series 13 Microfilm
Series 14 Audiotapes
Merrill G. Burlingame was born in Boone, Iowa on March 13, 1901, the son of Nathan and Teresa Gildea Burlingame. He attended local schools prior to receiving his doctorate at the University of Iowa in 1936. In 1929 he joined the faculty of Montana State College (now Montana State University) and became chair of the history department in 1935. Burlingame's research interests were primarily concerned with Montana and the frontier west. His books include: The Montana Frontier, (1942); A History of Montana (with K. Ross Toole, 1956); A History of Montana State University (1968); John M. Bozeman, Montana Trailmaker (1971). Burlingame also contributed articles to Mississippi Valley Historical Review, Pacific Northwest Quarterly, and Montana: The Magazine of Western History. Along with Dr. Caroline McGill, Burlingame helped establish the Museum of the Rockies and was active in the Montana Historical Society, the Montana Institute of the Arts, the American Historical Society, the Christian Church, and the Masonic fraternity. He married Virginia Struble in 1936 and the couple had one son, Ray. Merrill Burlingame died in Bozeman, Montana on November 14, 1994.
Primarily research files, the Burlingame papers reflect his lifelong interests in the history of Montana and the American West. The files have been arranged in 14 series based on subject or format. Subjects particularly heavily represented are: the history of Bozeman and Gallatin County, Montana and associated individuals; the history of Montana State University and associated individuals; the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ); Captain Gustavus C. Doane, Second U.S. Cavalry; Montana Native Americans. Series based on format are clippings, photographs, microfilm, maps, and audiotapes, all of which contain material represented in the subject series. There is also a small group of personal papers containing familial correspondence and genealogical information on the Burlingame family. Original documents created or collected by the William W. Alderson family, Gustavus C. Doane, and Harriette Cushman are also part of the Burlingame papers.
Original and photocopied correspondence, research notes, literary manuscripts, photographs, microfilm, and audiotapes created or collected by Merrill Burlingame were originally maintained by him in several four-drawer filing cabinets during the lengthy course of his career. The subject headings Burlingame assigned to the various folders were not consistent, and much repetition in these headings occurred over the years as he added to his collection. This duplication, along with Burlingame's practice of producing multiple carbon copies of his letters and notes, resulted in a great deal of redundancy in his filing system. The present arrangement represents a compromise between preserving Burlingame's original arrangement and efficiency in retrieval for researchers. Researchers should be cautioned, however, of the need to check the inventories of more than one series for pertinent material due to the difficulty in properly classifying the folder subject headings within any particular group. An asterisk (*) following a folder title indicates that material (either photographs or oversize documents) has been removed for storage elsewhere in the collection.
Burlingame, Merrill G. (Merrill Gildea), 1901-1994--Archives; Alderson, William W. (William White), 1831-1906; Cushman, Harriette Eliza, 1890-1978; Doane, Gustavus Cheyney, 1840-1892
Christian Church (Disciples of Christ); Montana State University--Bozeman--Faculty; Montana State University--Bozeman--History; United States-Army-Cavalry, 2nd
Alderson family; Burlingame family; Alderson family; Burlingame family
Bozeman (Mont.)--History; Gallatin County (Mont.)--History; Montana--History; West (U.S.)--History; Montana; Bozeman (Mont.)
Frontier and pioneer life--West (U.S.); Indians of North America-Montana-History; Names, Geographical-Montana; Historians-Montana-Bozeman; Agriculture; Railroads; Frontier and pioneer life
Archeology; Colleges and Universities; Elementary and Secondary Education; Military; Expeditions and Adventure; Native Americans; Pioneers; Railroads; Religion; Water and Water Rights; Idaho; Montana; Bozeman; Photographs; Sound Recordings
Biographies--Montana--Bozeman (Mont.); Biographies--Montana--Gallatin County (Mont.); Biographies--Montana; Biographies; Biography; Photographs; Photographs
- Biographical files, 1
  Notes, letters, printed materials, photocopied and original documents pertaining to a wide variety of historical personages, mostly connected with the development of Montana. In addition to the research notes that Burlingame created, some files contain actual manuscript materials created or collected by the biographical subject. While some of the subjects represented in this series figured prominently in the development of Gallatin County, most substantial biographical files of Gallatin County pioneers have been placed in series 2. There are also research files of a biographical nature in series 3, Montana and the Pioneer West. The materials in this series have been arranged alphabetically by the name of the biographical subject.
  - Ahern, George P. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, W.A. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amadeus, Mother (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anceney, Charles (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anceney, Charles (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anceney, Charles (nitrate negatives)* (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aronson, J. Hugo (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ashley, Governor James M. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baker, I.G. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beall, William (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bell, Edward J. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bell, William H. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blackmore, William (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Blair, Dr. James Franklin (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blakeley, Charles P. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Blankenship, Tom (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bottler, Frederick (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bovey, Charles A. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bowers, Bertha (TU Ranch) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bozeman, John* (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brackett, William S. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brainard, Laura (Box 1, Folder 21a)
  - Brewer, Helen R. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Brown, Frank Dean "Sandbar" (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Burnett, William (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Calamity Jane (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cameron, Evelyn J. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Campbell, Fannie (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Campbell, Col. Robert (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Carnahan, J.M. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Carter, Thomas Henry (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chase, Mary Ellen (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chesnut, James D. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Christman, Charles (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Clagett, William H. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clark, William (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Colter, John (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Colter, John (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Colter, John (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Colter, John (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Comstock, Henry T.P.* (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Conner, Pearl B. and Stuart (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cook, A.B. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cook, Charles W. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cooper, Gary (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cooper, Walter (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Crosby, Governor J. Schuyler (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Culbertson, Alexander (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Culbertson, Joseph (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Custer, George A.* (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Danner, Seth Orin (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Daugherty, John B. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Davidson, W.S. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Decker Family (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - DeLacy, W.W. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - DeSmet, Father (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dimsdale, Thomas J. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Duncan, Lewis J. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dunne, William F. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Edgar, Henry F. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Edgerton, Governor Sidney (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Edwards, Caldwell (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fairweather, Bill (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fetcher, Helen (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Finley, Francois (Benetsee) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Flaherty, Marie (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Flanders, G.W. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fletcher, Nellie (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fulton, Dan (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Garcia, Andrew (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - George, James (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Grant, Richard (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Griffith, Joseph Milton (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Grouard, Frank (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hartt, Rollin L. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Harris, Willard (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Heath, Capt. U.H. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Heikkila, Frank (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Henry, Dutch (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hepburn, John (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hosmer, Judge H.L. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Howard, Joseph Kinsey (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Howard, Dr. Wade (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Howes, Calvin C. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Howse, Joseph (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hoyt, Dr. Mary Dickins (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hunter, Duncan (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jaycox, W.W. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Johnston/Reichman families (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Kagy, John M. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Kelly, J.N. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - King, Thomas Wylie* (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Kipp Family (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Kirkaldie, Franklin (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Koch, Christian and Peter (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Kohrs, Conrad (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Krattcer, George Washington (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Krieg, Fred C. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Laliberte, Lorraine (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lamme Family (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Larrabee, Charles X. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lewis, Meriwether (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lewis, Sam (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lindley, Viola (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Long Hair, Chief (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - McGill, Dr. Caroline (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Meagher, Thomas F. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Melton, Amos (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Merrian, Harold G. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Monforton, Mr. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Monroe, Hugh (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Montgomery, Anne (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Moser, Dexter (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Mushbach, J.E. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Neihart, Sarah (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Nelson, "Doc" and Piersdorff, Lester (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Nelson, Harold T. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Norris L. Merlin (Scrapbook) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Patten, F.E.W. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Patten, George Y. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Peterson, Jacob L. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Phillips, Paul C. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pitts Family (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Plummer, Mr. and Mrs. Henry (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Potts, Governor Benjamin (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pryor, Nathaniel (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Purple, Edwin R. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ramsdall Journal (Do Not Reproduce) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Rankin, Jeannette (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Reichman Family (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Rich, Franklin W.* (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Roberts, William Milnor (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Robertson, Frank C. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Rouse, Daniel Elliott (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Russell, Charles M. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Sacajawea (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Sanders, Wilbur F. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Schultz, Mr. and Mrs. James W. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Shedd, James A. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Simmons, Major A.J. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Smith, Governor Green Clay (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Stapleton, Judge G.W. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Stasso, Lasso (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Steamboat Bill (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Storrs, Lucius Seynour (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Story, Nelson (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Stuart, Granville (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Sublette, William (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Sutherlin, Robert H. and William H. (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Thomas Party, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Thoroughman, Robert P. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Timmons, Mary* (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Tomlinson, Philo (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Toole, K. Ross (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Toponce, Alexander (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tracy, Mrs. William H. (Sarah J.) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tufts, James (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Van Orsdel, W.W. "Brother Van" (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Voldseth, Nels (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Walton, Roy (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Walsh, Senator Thomas J. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Wheeler, Burton K. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - White, Benjamin F. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - William, Captain James (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Willson, Fred F. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Wilson, James S.R. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Winnemucca, Sarah (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Yates, Granny (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Gallatin County research files, 2
  Notes, correspondence, photocopies, and original documents pertaining to the history of Gallatin County, Montana and the city of Bozeman, Montana. The topically labeled folders cover a wide variety of people, places, and events associated with Gallatin County history. Original documents created or collected by the W. W. Alderson family are included with this series as are files of biographical information on many prominent local personalities. Again, other biographical files of prominent Montanans can be found in series 1, Biographical files and series 3, Montana and the Frontier West. Research materials pertaining to Montana State College (Montana State University) in Bozeman have been placed in series 7. Much of the material dealing with the Christian Church in this series pertains to Burlingame's historical research on the Bozeman congregation and original copies of the Bozeman church's newspaper. For other Christian Church materials of a personal nature see series 8 and 10.
  - Alderson family - diary Centennial Project Proposal (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Alderson family - plan for publishing diary (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Alderson family - diaries, miscellaneous notes (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Alderson family - diaries, revisions (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Alderson family - diary, master, pp. 1-103 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Alderson family - diary, master, pp. 104-206 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Alderson family - original documents, 1868-1900 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Alderson family - transcripts of letters (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Archaeology (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Bader, John (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Bates, Grace (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Battle Ridge (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Belgrade (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Benepe, Frank L. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Benham Family (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Big Horn Gun* (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Blacktail Mountain Caves (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Bozeman Academy (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bozeman Arbor Day (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bozeman Cannery Company (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bozeman Cannery Company (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bozeman Cannery Company (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bozeman Chamber of Commerce (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Bozeman Chamber of Commerce- report, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bozeman Christmas (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bozeman churches (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Bozeman churches (Catholic) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) "Christian Worker" (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) "Christian Worker" (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Bozeman churches (Christian) "Christian Worker" (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Bozeman City Hall (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bozeman City Managers (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bozeman City Managers (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bozeman City Managers (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bozeman City Planning and Preservation (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Bozeman City Planning and Preservation (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Bozeman Deaconess Hospital History (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Bozeman early history (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Bozeman First National Bank (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Bozeman "firsts" (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Bozeman Government (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Bozeman Government (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Bozeman Heritage (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Bozeman Hillcrest Residents' Childhood Memories (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Bozeman Historic Survey (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Bozeman Homes (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Bozeman Incidents (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Bozeman Kirk Historic District (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Bozeman Newspapers (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Bozeman Opera House (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Bozeman Palace Theater (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Bozeman Prostitutes (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Bozeman Schools (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Bozeman Streets and Buildings (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Bozeman Sweet Pea Carnival (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Bozeman Weather (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Bridger Canyon (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bridger Canyon Christian Church (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Buffalo Jump (Madison)* (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Buffalo Jump (Madison) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Cement Plant (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Cemeteries (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Centennial/Territorial Preliminary Planning (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Central Park (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Chesnut/Chestnut (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Churchill, Montana (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Clarkston Valley (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Crail Ranch (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Culver Place (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Dry Creek Church (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - East Gallatin (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Ebbers, Jack (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Electric Railway (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Escaped Prisoner (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Fairs (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Flanders Sawmill (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Fort Ellis* (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Fort Ellis School (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Fort Ellis Sundial (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Fossils (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Gallatin Canyon/Big Sky (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Gallatin Canyon Indian Campground (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Gallatin Canyon - Levinski Case (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gallatin Century of Progress (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Gallatin City (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Gallatin City (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Gallatin County (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Gallatin County (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Gallatin County Government (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Gallatin County records (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Gallatin County High School (Programs and cards) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Gallatin County High School Newspaper, 1927 September (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Gallatin County Places and Things (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Gallatin Gateway (Salesville) (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Gallatin National Forest Map (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Gallatin Trust and Savings Bank Mural (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Gallatin Valley (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Gallatin Valley (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Gallatin Valley Female Seminary (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Gallatin Valley Female Seminary (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Gallatin Valley Railway (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Gallatin Valley/West Yellowstone (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Geisdorff, Dr. and Aimes, E.B. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Ghost Towns (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Gold (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Hamilton (3 miles south of Manhattan) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Headwaters Academy (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Headwaters Bicentennial Project (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Headwaters Herald (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Headwaters State Park (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Highway Sights and Interests (Gardiner-Livingston-Bozeman) (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Horseshoe Hills (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Hot Springs (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Hunter, Bill (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Hyalite Canyon (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Indians (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Jails and Courthouses (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - July 4 in Bozeman (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Karst, Pete (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Kenney/Rhoten Diary (1864-1867) (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Kent, Irving Cabin (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Kenyon, Carlisle (interview) (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Leverich Canyon (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Lewis and Clark Pageant (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Mammoth Ditch Company (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Manhattan, Montana (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Medical Care (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Murray Cabin (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Nixon Bridge (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Pageants (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Parks (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Ross Peak (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Sacajawea Hotel (Three Forks) (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Sawmills (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - School Districts (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Sedan (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Spring Hill (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Stage Routes (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Story Quilt (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Street/Roads Names (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Summit Engineering Corp (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Three Forks (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Three Forks* (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Three Forks Bicentennial Celebration (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Three Forks Bicentennial Celebration (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Timberline, Montana (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Timberline, Montana (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Toll Roads and Ferries (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Tours (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Trail Creek and Storrs, Montana (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Upper Gallatin Geological History (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Willow Creek (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Willson Company (Box 13, Folder 24)
- Montana and the pioneer west, 3
  Notes, correspondence, photocopies, and original documents pertaining to the history of Montana and the pioneer west. These topically arranged folders cover a wide variety of material that documents Burlingame's research interests in Montana's past beyond Gallatin County and Bozeman. Original documents created or collected by Captain Gustavus C. Doane and his wife, Mary Hunter Doane, are included in this series, along with drafts of an unpublished manuscript biography of Doane written by Burlingame in the late 1930s and early 1940s. Some material on Montana Native Americans is included in this series, usually in the context of the Indian Wars and the frontier military. More complete research in this area is represented in series 6, Indians.
  - Acquisition List, Fall 1964 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Agricultural History Symposium, 1976 June (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture in the Great Plains, 1876-1930 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Alder Gulch Discoveries (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - "American West, Perpetual Images" (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Americana Encyclopedia (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Antiquity Act (Montana), 1974 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Anaconda (Education) (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Arbor Day in Montana (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Archaeology* (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Archaeology* (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Archaeology - Bibliography (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Archaeology - Burial Rocks* (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Archaeology - Canada (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Archaeology - Caves and Pictographs* (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Arsenal (Montana) (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Ashley, Governor James (Box 14, Folder 18)